<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triall of the English liturgie, or A copie of a letter, wherein severall exceptions and arguments against the imposition and use of the service book in the English churches, are set forth and discussed. Written by a reverend divine, to his Christian friend, for his private satisfaction in this particular. And now published for publicke good</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14543</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844396</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178375</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248509243</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 16452.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S93928</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99844396e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1633:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triall of the English liturgie, or A copie of a letter, wherein severall exceptions and arguments against the imposition and use of the service book in the English churches, are set forth and discussed. Written by a reverend divine, to his Christian friend, for his private satisfaction in this particular. And now published for publicke good</title>
                  <author>Davenport, John, 1597-1670, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Christiaens],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Leiden] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the yeare 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to John Davenport.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in: Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178375:1"/>
            <p>THE TRIALL <hi>OF</hi> The English Liturgie, <hi>OR</hi> A Copie of a Letter, wherein seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall EXCEPTIONS and ARGVMENTS against the imposition and use of the Service Book in the English Churches, are set forth and discussed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WRITTEN</hi> By a Reverend Divine, to his Christian Friend, for his private satisfaction in this particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now published for publicke good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the yeare</hi> 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:178375:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178375:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Copy of a Letter,</hi> VVherein severall Exceptions and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, against the imposition and use of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Booke in the English Churches, are set forth and discussed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SJR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I am senseable of the ill enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement which the trueth in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular hath found with those who are wont to slight the grounds which they examine not, and of the reproaches, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and dangers, whereunto they are exposed who beare witnesse to it, yet every trueth is pretious and more worth then my name, liberty or life, which I have good reason to despise for his sake, who hath emptied himselfe of all his Glory, and humbled himselfe to the death, even the death of the Crosse, for mee, and therefore in assurance of your unfained Love of the Trueth, &amp; of Mee for the Trueths sake: to satisfie your earnest desire, I put Pen to Paper for your help in that Question, concerning the Liturgie imposed upon the Churches, and used by them for solemne worshippe in Assemblies: Examine what I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178375:3"/>write by the Scripture, as in the sight and feare of our GOD, whose yealousie is made knowen from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven against those who presume to worshippe him by mens inventions and appoyntments, and if it agree with the Scripture, receave it for the Truet s sake, if not, reject it.</p>
            <p>AGainst this Prayer Booke divers men have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded after a diffrent maner. First, some Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are proper to the Separatists (<hi>quatalis</hi>) <hi>viz.</hi> That it is offered up in a false Church. Secondly, With a false Minister. 3. In the behalfe of the Subjects of the Kingdome of Antichrist: these are properly theirs, being the grounds whereupon they make a totall Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from all the Churches in this Land, as no Churches of CHRIST; these I approve not, yet note them, that you may see upon how different grounds the same Position is maintained by severall persons, and that you may be delivered from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice which hinders many from receaving those trueths, because they feare the reproach of <hi>Brownisme.</hi> Secondly, there are other grounds which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all that plead for the purity of Christs Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, and which doeth not necessarily inferre such Separation, but onely serve to shew the unlawfulnesse of that practise, and of our communicating therein, to which purpose I am to shew two things: First, What our exceptions are against the Service Booke: Secondly, how just they are.</p>
            <p>First, the exceptions against it, are; First, That it is devised by men, (<hi>viz.</hi>) other men whom God hath
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178375:3"/>not called to such a work as to invent formes of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which should bee used by all the Churches in a Land, for their Prayer: Secondly, That it is imposed upon the Minister and people of necessitie: Thirdly, That it is stinted both in matter &amp; words, to be used without variation: Fourthly, That it is read out of a Booke that is many wayes saulty and corrupt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the justnesse of these exceptions against it, may be declared by Reasons. The first Reason, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God did never commaund to use nor promise to except such a Worship. In which respect it is a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest breach of the second Commandement, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. vers. 4.5.6. For if the Booke of Prayers were means of God worship, ordayned by God, surely he would have given some light and ground for them in his Word in the olde Testament, if ever it had been need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to have helped them with a forme of publike Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, God would have devised one for them, or have given power to the Priestes and Levites to have prescribed one to them, during the minoritie and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogie of that Church. But wee finde no syllable of any sucsi matter in all the Law &amp; the Prophets: what formes are there mentioned, are but for some speciall occasions, and commanded to the Church, (which I pray observe) not from every ordinary Church Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, Priests and Levites, but onely from the Prophets, who had an extraordinarie and immediate calling from God, &amp; who might as well deliver for Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Oracles, the trueth of God taught by them, as any formes of Prayers or Prayses.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> But we see a Forme of blessing is appointed to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178375:4"/>used by <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sonnes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.24.25.26. Therefore a forme of prayers may by appointed to the Minister.</p>
            <p>There is an apparant difference betweene Prayer &amp; Blessing, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> in the sence of that place; for Prayer is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed from men to God, but blessing in the sence of that place is pronounced from God to Man, and therefore the Lord saith, <hi>Thus shalt thou blesse the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Israell, and say unto them,</hi> vers. 2.3. not unto God. And <hi>Solomon</hi> used a different gesture in praying, and in blessing the people, to note the difference betweene them, for in praying for them he kneeled, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 8.4.5. but hee stood up when he blessed the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>vers.</hi> 55. according to the rule <hi>Deutronomie</hi> 10.8.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if that blessing were a Prayer, yet it will not thence appeare that set formes are lawfull; for there are who give divers reasons to prove that <hi>Moses</hi> in that place did not prescribe unto the Priests a forme of wordes whereunto they must bee tyed in blessing of the people, but only gave them a rule or direction according to which they should blesse them, nor can the contrary be proved from the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If it were a stinted forme, yet it was not devised by men, but by God himselfe, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Moses</hi> to appoint <hi>Aaron</hi> thus to blesse the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. From Gods appointing a forme of words of his owne devising, to bee used in blessing of the people in his Name; it will not therefore follow, that man may appoint a forme of words devised by other men, to be used by the Minister praying in the name of the Congregation to God.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:178375:4"/>
            <p> A set Forme is used in singing of Psalmes; <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> it may be used also in Prayer.</p>
            <p>Singing of Psalmes, and Praying, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> differ many wayes:</p>
            <p>First, many Psalmes are for Instruction onely, wherein is not a word of petition, and those Psalmes which containe Prayers, are written for our instruction, &amp; serve to teach us in what maner we should pray on like occasions, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. as all Scriptures were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. and are profitable to teach, 2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3.16. But as the reading of them is not the praying of the Church, so neither is the sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, which is but loud speaking as it were in a certaine harmonie or tune: the Church praying, for instance the 102. Psalme, is intitled <hi>A Trayer of the afflicted,</hi> yet it was not imposed or devised to bee said by every man for his prayer in affliction, but it serves to teach us in what maner we should powre out our complaints before the Lord in such cases, and we may, if wee will, take such expressions thence, as may best suite with our occasions, not stinting our selves to those words alone.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in Prayer, the Minister alone uttereth the wordes, the people adding their <hi>Amen</hi> in the end, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.6. but in singing, every person in the Church pronounceth every word and sillable aloud, and in a tune, <hi>Ergo,</hi> there is a necessitie of having formes of P<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>almes set downe in words, not so of Prayers.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Psalmes are parts of Scriptures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God speaketh unto us, teaching and instructing us, &amp; we our selves, &amp; one another mutually, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.19.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178375:5"/>
               <hi>Collos.</hi> 3.16. therefore it is necessarie to be expressed in wordes; but in Prayer wee speak to God, according to severall occasions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Penmen of the Psalmes were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, extraordinarily assisted and immediatly by God designed to that worke, so are not the Authours of the Liturgie.</p>
            <p>A set Forme of Prayer was appointed to bee used when the Arke went forward, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> and when it rested, <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.34.35.36.</p>
            <p>It doth not appeare that it was appointed: the Text saith, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Moses sayd these vvords,</hi> but not that hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed others to say so, whensoever the Arke should goe forward or rest. 2. If <hi>Moses</hi> did appoint it, yet that is no warrant for us; for <hi>Moses</hi> was a Prophet, and had an immediat commission from God for what hee appointed in the house of God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.2. which the Imposers of the Liturgie can not plead. 3. This Prayer of <hi>Moses</hi> was but on a particular occasion, and (for ought I know) not used by others after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: for wee finde no mention of it in divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves of the Arke in <hi>Iosuas</hi> time, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.4. to <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. and in <hi>Samuels</hi> time, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.7. and in <hi>Davids</hi> time, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.15. Now, to plead for the lawfulnesse of a set Forme, devised and imposed by other men, upon the Ministers to be alwayes used, from a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie act of <hi>Moses,</hi> used on a particular occasion, but not imposed upon posteritie: what congruetie is therein, judge you.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour Christ hath given a Forme of Prayer to be used by us, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label>
               <hi>Math.</hi> 6. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. therefore a Forme
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178375:5"/>of Prayer devised, and imposed by other men, upon the Minister, is lawfull.</p>
            <p>I denie the Argument, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> for will it follow that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Christ may devise and impose a forme, therefore men may doe it? to parralell this with other things, Christs ordinance can make the writings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles a rule of Faith, can men make another Scripture? or can they appoint their Homelies to be used &amp; read in the Churches as the Prophets &amp; Apostles did their writings? Indeed, such a pretence is put upon their Hommelie or Exhortation, added to the prayers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the last publike Fasts, that as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles wrote certaine Epistles, which they caused to be read in the Churches, so certaine Apostolicall men, had written this Exhortation, &amp;c. You may reade the words in the Booke whereunto I referre you, not having it at hand. Now if this Title <hi>(viz.)</hi> as Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall men, they pleade their right to prescribe formes to the Churches, let them shew the signes of Apostles, <hi>viz.</hi> that they have heard and seene Christ as the Apostles did, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.21.22. and 22.14. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1.2. that they have an immediate calling, not of man, nor by man, but of Christ, <hi>Gallat.</hi> 1.1.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they have a generall commission to goe forth into all the world, to plant Churches, and are qualified with the gifts of tongues, &amp;c. for that purpose, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that they have infallible assistance of the spirit in all things they impose upon the Churches, and Christs commaund for the things which they teach men to observe and to doe, as the Apostles had,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178375:6"/>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. if not, they will be found false Apostles, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.2. and must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that plea, else both their office &amp; impositions are to be rejected as Antichristian. Againe, Christ can appoint Sacraments which men cannot doe, yet these who presume to devise a Liturgie for all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, are so bould also as to obtrude upon them teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing signes, <hi>viz.</hi> significant ceremonies, as if the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which Christ hath appointed, were not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for that purpose, in which respect the Churches ought the more resolutely to set themselves against all humane devises &amp; incroachements in the matters of Religion, lest a newe rule of Faith in time be devised and imposed by men, as it is in the Papacie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what if this forme be not imposed by our Saviour, to the end that beleevers should be tyed onely to those words in prayer, as indeed it is not, as wee shall an one shew, in answere of the first objection, of the second particular, in the third Reason: Will this at all countenance the impositions of the Liturgie upon the Churches? not at all.</p>
            <p>A second Reason: because it is Gods Ordinance that the Churches should bee edefyed by their gifts who minister unto thē, &amp; that in Prayer aswell as in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which I prove in this Order; First, that Prayer and Preaching in the Church are two especiall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Minister, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.2.4. where Praying, could not bee reading Prayers out of a Booke, as neither could the Ministery of the Word, be reading of an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, for to serve Tables, would not hinder them from eyther of these.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:178375:6"/>
            <p> Secondly, Christ fitteth all his servants with gifts for the whole worke of the Ministri, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.8.11.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.6. he that hath made them able ministers of the new Testament, hath enabled them to pray, as well as to Preach by their owne gifts; For, Prayer is an ordinance of the new Testament as well as Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and they are made able thereunto, not by shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the sufficiency of other men, whose Prayer they read, but their sufficiency is of God, enabling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; so that, if any be not gifted for those workes, the Worde doth not warrant the having of them for Ministers of Christ, if they be endued with gifts fit for those workes, the Word doth not warrant the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing to them stinted Prayers or Homelyes, and why may they not as lawfully commaund them to Preach by reading of Homelies, as to pray by reading of the Liturgie?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The mastifestation of the spirit, every gift in declaring whereof the spirit is manifested, is given not onely to some men that lived in former times, but to every man, much more to the man of God to profit with all, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. For what is there sayd of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie gifts, holdes by proportion in all gifts, especially Ministeriall: but what Ministerial gift is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised and manifested in reading Prayers, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry childe of 12 or 13 yeares olde, is sufficiently able to doe.</p>
            <p>Reading of Scripture is a Ministeriall dutie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> and therefore why not reading of Prayers also?</p>
            <p>Between publike reading of Scriptures, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> &amp; publike reading of Prayers, there are at least two differences.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178375:7"/>First, the publike reading of Scripture is Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, (so is not the other:) The reading of the Law and Prophets is mentioned as parts of Gods publike worshippe, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.15. But there is no mention from <hi>Moses</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> of any Liturgie devised by man, which might not have beene consealed, if it had bene for the edification of the Church, to set up such meanes of Gods worshippe as Liturgies read publikely for the Prayers of the Church. Secondly, Reading of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures simply considered in it selfe, in the publike As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, is not the proper worke of the Minister, but may be done by any member, whom the Church shall appoint thereunto, though hee be no Minister, as the maner is in the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas, but the reading ofte whole Liturgie is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to every man, but only such as are made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters by the Prelates: now seeing they make such ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this peece of service, as appropriate it to the Minister to read the Liturgie, and to binde him so strictly to the use of it, as they doe, it concernes both Ministers and People, to see that it be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Worde so to be used in the Churches.</p>
            <p>The reading of the Liturgie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> hinders not the use of their owne gifts afterwards in the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>If the Worde enjoynes the exercise of his owne gift in Prayer as well as in Preaching, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> &amp; doth not give warrant to the introducing of any other formes, by mens devise and appoyntment, wee must be carefull as not to take from the Word any ordinance of God, so not to adde to the Word, as meanes of worshipping God by the devises &amp; appointment of men. 2. If they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178375:7"/>may limit them in the Deske, why not in the Pulpit also? 3. The Canon also stintes them accordingly a forme alwayes to be used in the Pulpit, see Canon 55. as well as in the Deske, &amp; in <hi>Norvvitch</hi> Diocesie that forme is pressed upon the Minister in the Pulpit, and Canonicall obedience binde them thereunto, who have yeelded themselves to be governed by these Canons &amp; Constitutions, so that at last the Church will come to be wholy deprived of the profit of their Ministers gifts, and Christ of the honour of them: for who sees not that the imposing of Prayers devised by other men upon the Churches, to be used by all Ministers ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily for theirs &amp; the Churches Prayer, doth much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the honour, fruit, and benefite of Christs Ascension into Heaven, &amp; from the love, care, &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that he hath, and shewes continually to his Church upon Earth, giving gifts to men, for the worke of the Ministerie, and the profite of the Churches, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.8. and the 13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.5.6. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third Reason: Because God hath appointed other helpes for Prayer, (which are sufficient without this.) First particular, the holy Ghost is given to teach us to pray as wee ought, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. the Spirit helpes our infirmities, who knowes not how to pray as wee ought. How doth it that? not by a Booke in reading, whereof the Minister offers up his owne, and the Churches Prayer to God, (for that will rather helpe them to more infirmities, and lesse abillities in Prayer) but it self makes requests: first, it provekes us to pray, and tels us as it were within, what we should pray, or frameth such desires within us, by which wee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178375:8"/>request God, as Expositers, of the best note, interpret that place.</p>
            <p>A Prayer made by others, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> and read out of a Booke, may be sayd to be made by the spirit of God: First, because it assisted him that made the Prayer: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because the spirit stirreth up his affections who reades the Prayers.</p>
            <p>This Objection the Apostle seemes to prevent when hee saith, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>The Spirit it selfe makes requests for us,</hi> viz. the spirit alone, either immediately (or by meanes sanctified and ordained by himselfe) makes requests for us, <hi>viz.</hi> who set our selves to pray (though with many infirmities) which also the worde following in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates, when hee gives this for the reason, why the spirit helpes our infirmities, for (saith hee) <hi>Wee know not hovv to pray as vvee ought.</hi> But if such read Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies were fufficient, it might bee sayd, though wee know not how to pray as wee ought, yet those that made the Liturgie knew how to pray, and wee pray their prayers; whence it will follow, that it is not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to the intent of that place, that others were assisted in making the Prayers which were read, and that our affections be stirred up in reading those Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, unlesse our understanding be directed, and our affections quickned by the holy Ghost, to expresse by our owne gifts, our owne requests when we pray for others, or for our selves, and that this is the true meaning of praying in the spirit, &amp; in the holy Ghost, will appeare in <hi>Gallat.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Iude</hi> vers. 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>The Prayer of the Minister is devised by man, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:178375:8"/>himselfe, and the people are limited by his Prayer, as much as by a Booke forme.</p>
            <p>The Question is not of Prayer devised by a mans selfe, or of limitting the spirit in the people, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> but of Prayer devised by others, and imposed, and of limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the spirit of the Minister; the first is lawfull, the second sinfull: for a man to devise his owne Prayer is a dutie, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. but to take up for his Prayer the devises of other men, &amp; to be bound to a constant use of them ordinarily, is no where warranted. Again, that the spirit of the people should joyne with the Ministers spirit in Prayer is an ordinance of Christ, who ordereth no more to their parts in that case then to joyne with him, and so testifie it by saying <hi>Amen,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16. and therefore it cannot be properly said, that the spirit is limitted by his owne ordinance, but when the spirit of the Minister is streightened by formes prescribed to him by men without Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and appointment, then the spirit is limitted, and stinted indeed.</p>
            <p>If the Minister prayes by a forme of his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vising, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> his spirit is thereby stinted, why may it not as well be stinted by booke prayer imposed?</p>
            <p>Although it be not safe for a Minister to limit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to one form of prayer alwayes, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> though devised by himselfe, yet the people may more safely joyne with him in that then in the other: for two Reasons. First, because that Prayer, being devised by himselfe, is an exercise of his gift in a measure, and his defect in not exercising it so much as hee should, is his owne personall sinne. Secondly, because it is not by mans
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178375:9"/>authoritie imposed upon him to use that forme, but voluntarilie taken up of himselfe, in which case, first they subject not themselves to mans ordināce in Gods worship, as they doe in the other. Secondly, he may the next day alter his forme, (for ought the people knowes) seeing he is free to use it or not, but in the other case, they know no other Prayer can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the people, or may be used by the Minister, then their Liturgie.</p>
            <p>If a forme were not imposed, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> but every Minister were left unto his owne way, great inconveniencie would follow.</p>
            <p>First, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> you see the Ministers exercise their owne gifts in Prayer in the Pulpit, without any inconveniencie following upon it: shew a reason why it is more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for them to take that libertie when they reade in the Deske, then when they preach in the Pulpit? Secondly, this objection casts an imputation upon Christ and the Scripture, as not having sufficiently provided against inconveniencies in Gods worship. Thirdly, if none bee admitted to the Ministry, but those whose fitnesse for the worke of the Ministrie is sufficiently knowen according to Christs ordinance, this inconveniencie need not to bee feared.</p>
            <p>A second particular: the Scripture holdes forth the forme of Prayer, given by Christ our Lord, for a rule and patterne according to which our Prayer should be framed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.1.4. and therefore men cannot adde other formes hereunto by their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without injury and dishonour to Christ our Lord: for will it not lay an imputation of imperfectiō
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178375:9"/>upon the Rule, and upon Christ, as not sufficiently provided for his Church? If a forme devised and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by men be good, seeing he hath left not rule for it in the Scripture, which should perfectly furnish the man of God to every good worke,<note n="(a)" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16 17.</note> &amp; is written to this end among others, that wee may know how wee ought to behave ourselves in the house of God.<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13 14.</note> &amp; therefore what is there in taught must be kept without spot unrebukeable, to the appearing of Christ,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.2. and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.32. <hi>Iosua</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30 5.6. <hi>Gall.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding thereto, or deminishing from it,<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev</hi> 22.13.</note> &amp; that under a dreadfull penalty denounced against those who shall presume to doe otherwise.</p>
            <p>First <hi>Objection,</hi> Christs appointing a forme, seemes to give allowance to formes devised by other men, for it shewes, that a Prayer not devised by a mans selfe, may be offered up to God for a mans owne Prayer, and if that be so, why may not other men devise a forme of Prayer, and impose it upon all the Churches to be used in the publike Assemblies?</p>
            <p>If Christ had appointed this forme to be used when we pray, as the wordes seeme to intimate, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. It will not thence follow that men may devise and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose their formes, but those 2. things will follow upon it: First, that men must see that Christs forme be used in the Church when they pray. Secondly, that no man presume to impose another forme of other mens devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon the Churches; for instance, suppose God had appointed <hi>Aaron</hi> blesse the people alwayes in that forme of words, spoken of <hi>Numbers</hi> the 6 Chapter, it would thence have followed, that <hi>Moyses</hi> must see to it that <hi>Aaron</hi> used that forme, &amp; might not suffer him to impose any other forme of words to be used by the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178375:10"/>Priests, in blessing the people, Prayer was typed by the insence or perfume, which every Morning and Evening was burnt before the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.7.8. compared with Psalm. 241.2. Now, when the Lord had devised &amp; appointed a perfume, all men are forbidden to make a composition like that perfume, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.35.37. so if it could be proved, that Christ had made that forme for a Prayer to be used by the Churches, and by beleevers, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes when they pray, thē the offering up of any other Prayers (made by others) or of our own devising, would seeme to be as unlawfull, as the offering of strange in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.9.</p>
            <p>Secondly, though it be true that Christ give us li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to use that for a Prayer, being uttered with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, yet his purpose is thereby to direct us how to frame all our Prayers, and not to tye us to say over these words for our Prayers, as may appeare by these reasons: First, because all the circumstances in both the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists, doth lead us to understand it thus, for in <hi>Mathevv</hi> it is part of Christs Sermon, wherein hee shewes, how Almes, &amp; Fastings, &amp; Prayer, are to be used aright with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ambition, Hypocrisie, Babbling: and in <hi>Luke</hi> hee shewes them how to come to God in Prayer, as Friends to their Friends, as Children to their Parents, asking Bread, Fish, &amp;c. and making their requests knowne to God, according to particular wants in Faith, Hope, Love, &amp;c. Secondly, because the two Evangelists doth not tye themselves to the same wordes, or number of wordes, in recording that forme of Praier which may seeme to be ordered by a speciall providēce, to prevent this conceit, for if wee be tyed to these wordes which Christ uttered, which Evangelist shall wee follow?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178375:10"/>Thirdly; because the Apostles did not bind themselves to those words, but used others, according to their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall occasions, and taught the Churches to whom they wrote (not) to say over those wordes, but according to their necessities and occasions, to shew their requests unto God, in all maner, prayer, and supplication in the spirit, &amp;c. But if Christ had tyed us to the use of those words, in that number and order, then it would bee a sinne to pray at any time without using those wordes, for hee saith, <hi>When you pray, say our Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this passage: If Christ, who is the Lord and Lawgiver to the Church, and knowing the minde of his Father, was able to frame a perfect and absolute Prayer for his Church, yet did not holde it meet to tye his people to those wordes alwayes which himselfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised, but left the Churches free therein; much lesse may any man impose their devised formes to be used of necessitie, ordained in the Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> taught his Disciples to pray, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 11.1. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore stinted Liturgies are lawfull.</p>
            <p>It doth not appeare in the Scripture, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> how <hi>Iohn</hi> taught his Disciples to pray, whether by giving them some rules &amp; directions, what petitions they should put up, and in what maner, or by composing a forme for them; if the former be meant, so may any man teach another to pray, &amp; those that have the education, &amp; instructing of oth<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, ought to teach those under their charge, but that wil give no countenance to set formes, wherof the question is. Againe, suppose that <hi>Iohn</hi> did propound some maner or forme of Prayer for the private use of his Disciples, yet it doth not serve to justifie the Liturgie in question: For, first, the times are not alike, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:178375:11"/>among the Iewes, was then so decayed, that it is most probable that there were but few which held the right order of Prayer. Secondly, the promised Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō being then at hand, it was necessarie that the mindes of the faithfull should be stirred up to hope and desire of the same; now, suppose <hi>Iohn,</hi> into divers places of Scripture, did fit some Prayer to the time, and to the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall kingdome of Christ, which hee now began to reveale, what is this to our times, who have a forme of Prayer sufficient for our direction and helpe, this way taught by Christ himselfe, which they wanted in <hi>Johns</hi> time, else I beleeve <hi>Iohn</hi> would have spared his paines in in this, and have referred them thereunto? Secondly, the maner of propounding them is not alike; for, <hi>Iohn</hi> indeed taught his Disciples how to pray in private, but did not tye them to those very words without variatiō, which may be thus evinced: Christ taught his Disciples to pray as <hi>Iohn</hi> taught his, but Christ did not so tye his Disciples, as hath beene proved: therefore <hi>Iohn</hi> did not his: and who can prove that <hi>Iohn</hi> prescribed them to use his words at all, for hee might give them a forme of words which they were not to use for their prayers, but to learne from thence how to order their owne prayers? and so the Psalmes, which are Prayers, serve to teach us how to pray in like cases, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. &amp; many Prayers, printed by good mē, may be used by those that are ignorant, to sh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w them hovv their Prayers should be framed, provided that they tye not themselves to use those formes for their daily prayers; but the Liturgie, in question, limits all the Churches to one forme to bee used of necessitie every Lords day for their publike prayers. Thirdly, the matter of them is not alike, for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178375:11"/>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> taught his Disciples to pray for such things as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with the minde of God in the Scripture, else Christ would have witnessed against that evill, and not have taught the Disciples to pray as <hi>Iohn</hi> taught his, but the Liturgie in question, imposeth such Prayers upon the Churches, wherewith a Beleever cannot joyne in faith, as shall be shewed in the sixth Reason.</p>
            <p>Other Reformed Churches have formes: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> they are lawfull.</p>
            <p>First, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> wee are not to consider what other Churches doe, but what they ought to doe, and what the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches, planted by the Apostles, did; who are patternes to them and us. Secondly those formes are not imposed upon all the Congregations of necessitie, to be used as these are, but are left free, as appeares in the Libertie they take in that particular without rebuke in the Low Countryes.</p>
            <p>Publike Prayers offered up by the Minister in Church Assemblies, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason. </seg>4</label> must be framed according to the present and severall occasions of the Church and people of God, (as also mens private Prayers ought to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) which can not be done when men are stinted to those formes: for instance, the Church prayed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the occasion, when one was to bee left in the place of <hi>Iudas, Actor.</hi> 1.34. and when the Apostles had beene threatened by the Counsell, <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.24. and when <hi>Peter</hi> was in prison, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.5. In like maner <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats the helpe of their prayers in requests suteable to this occasion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.30.31.32. 2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.12. and this is implyed when all Beleevers are called upon to watch unto prayer, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:178375:12"/>
            <p> In the Liturgie there are prayers for many occasions, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> as, change of Weather, times of Warre, Pestilence, Famine, Visitation of the sicke, Marriage, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet there are many other occasions of particular use for that Congregation, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> &amp; for others, which that Booke points not at; as, the choosing of Officers; as, Pastors, Teachers, Elders and Deacons, by the Church, and many other cases, wherein the Church should meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, according to Christs ordinance, beside those mentioned in the Text of Scripture before alledged. For proofe of this fourth Reason, none of which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions are fitted with any Prayer in the Liturgie. 2. Those occasions whereunto some Prayers are fitted, should be expressed by the Minister in such words as may have reference to the severall states &amp; conditions of their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Congregations respectively, which is parte of their watching over their flocke, but the Booke doth not this, nor can doe it.</p>
            <p>Because the worship of God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason </seg>5</label> by that stinted forme whereof our question is, is the devise of Antichrist, it being neerer prescribed or used in the primative Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches planted by the Apostles, and recorded in Scripture, but as the mistery wrought to a greater height in decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning times of the Church, it was receaved by little and little, till at last it came to be compleatly framed, strictly injoyned, and every where used in the Papacy, as ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to maintaine superstition, and a dumbe Idoll, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ministery; and to nourish people in ignorance of the nature and right use of Prayer: the Masse Booke is in Latine, this Liturgie Booke is in English; the Masse Booke hath all the Prayers this Liturgie hath, and some more; other differences I know not betweene them.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178375:12"/>Therefore King <hi>Edvvard</hi> the sixth in his Letter to the <hi>Devonshire men,</hi> to convince them, that their Liturgie was none Service, tels them, That it is no other but the olde, &amp; the selfe same words in English which were in Latine, save a few things taken out, which were so fonde that it was a shame to heare them in English: and King <hi>Iames</hi> in a Speech of his in <hi>Scotland,</hi> sayd, That their English Liturgie was an ill sayd Masse, and this is made the first of the exceptions against the Common Prayer Booke, which were briefly added too, in the Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it appointed a Liturgie, which in the whole matter &amp; form thereof, is too like unto the Masse Book.</p>
            <p>But the wordes and Petitions are good in those Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> therefore the Booke may be lawfully used.</p>
            <p>Not all the words and Petitions are good, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> as will be shewed in the sixth Reason. Secondly, good words expressing good Petitions, are not sufficient to prove that their Prayers are good: For, first, a Prayer may be good without words, as the mentall Prayer of <hi>Annah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.12.15. Secondly, In vocall Prayer more is required to make it good thē good words, <hi>viz.</hi> Among other things, this, that it proceed from the ability which the spirit of God bestowes on him who utters the words to fit his requests, to the present occasion, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15.16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7.</p>
            <p>Some of those Exiled in Queene <hi>Maryes</hi> dayes, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> for witnessing against Antechrist, pleaded for this Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie in <hi>Franckeforde,</hi> &amp; in the beginning of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, godly men approved it, and rejoyced in it, and since, holy men have used &amp; defended it, therefore it may lawfully bee used.</p>
            <p>First, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> I deny the Argument, more particular and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178375:13"/>distinctly I answere: First, that the Booke then plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, was made in <hi>Edward</hi> the sixts time, and against it M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Knox</hi> and others witnessed in <hi>Frankeford;</hi> yea, though his life was indangered thereby, and the loosing of his estate followed upon it; yet he would not receave it into the Church, though some pleaded for it, who were not so troughly purged from all Antichristian lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as was to bee wished, though they witnessed a good confession against the Masse, and Transsubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c. Secondly, In the beginning of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, godly men rejoyced not so much in the Prayers, as that the worship of God was celebrated in our owne Language, whereas before it was in Latine, which few understood. Thirdly, holy mens using and defending it in these dayes, doth not prove it more lawfull then Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligamy and the taking of Concubines, was to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before Christ, which they used and were ready to defend, if any had spoken against it: in those dayes, the holy Apostles are not to be followed otherwise then as they follovv Christ, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. The Ievves at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> was missed by following <hi>Peters</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, though a Pillar in the Church without a Rule, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13. Fourtly, In the time of ignorance God passed them by, and us also. But now he admonisheth all men, to whom the trueth is revealed, to repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30.</p>
            <p>The Prayer Booke in question, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason. </seg>6</label> is corrupt in many things: First, the matter of some Petitions, is such as wee cannot say <hi>Amen</hi> to it in faith, as may be instanced insome Collects, as to instance ne or 2. for a taste. In the Collect on the 12. Sunday after Trinity, is prayed, that God would forgive us those things whereof our cōsciences are afraid, &amp; to give unto us that our prayers
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178375:13"/>dare not presume to aske. In the Collect for Innocents day, it is said: Almighty God, whose prayse this day the young Innocents thy witnesses have confessed, and shewed forth, not in speaking, but in dying: And in one of the Collects to bee used for Morning Prayer every Lords day, you pray for Bishops and Curates, and all Congregations cōmitted to their charge: Now, if Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations be not committed to Diocesan Bishops, as they say they are, (pure Divines) and if Pastors of Churches bee not their Curates in all the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or if the Curats under the Pastors of the Churches bee not Christs ordinance, then you pray, that plants which God hath not planted, should prosper in the Churches, which cannot be done in Faith. To omit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, the very fitting of Collects to certaine dayes, for holy Fasts, and Feasts not sanctified by God, savour of superstition; as, speciall Prayers for Lent, ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to countenance the keeping of it as a Religious Fast, and the Collect on good Friday, and on the holy dayes. Secondly, The maner of Praying vaine Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; as, the often repeating the Lords Prayer; &amp;, Glory to the Father, &amp;, Lord have mercy upon us, &amp;c. not out of fervency as <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel</hi> did,<note place="margin">See the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of the Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Pag. <hi>2.</hi> to the 16.</note> but out of forme meerely, this is expresly condemned <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.12 Disorderly Responsaries, the Clarke taking a parte of the Prayer out of the Ministers mouth, contrary to the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.40. which also introduceth an office into the Church, which God never appointed; as also, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Curats are contrary to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 44.8. Now, the Prayer which we cannot offer up in Faith, is contrary to <hi>Roman.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. v. 6. and Chap. 12.28.29.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Besides the Booke, which for these Prayers
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:178375:14"/>sakes, is brought into the Church, perverteth the right use of the Scripture, dismembreth &amp; mishappieth them for making of Gospels, Epistles, Lessons and Collects, appointed for Feasts of mens devising, &amp; derived from the Papists, and it retaines a corrupt translation of the Psalmes, &amp; bringeth into the Church Apocrypha wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and the errours contained in them.</p>
            <p>Some things may be found amisse in the Prayers of Ministers, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> when they exercise their owne gifts, with which a man cannot joyne in Faith, yet that which is good is not to bee rejected for that which is evill, and why not in this case also?</p>
            <p>When the Minister exerciseth his owne gift, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> Gods ordinance is observed, where with I may communicate in Praying, as well as in Preaching, notwithstanding his infirmities in either, which are but personall and in such cases the Rule warranteth men to try all things, &amp; to hold that which is good, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 5.21. But when the Liturgie is read, an ordinance which is not of God, but of man, is introduced into Gods Worship, contrary to the second Commandement, and therefore I must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it, and have no communion with it.</p>
            <p>Suppose these stinted formes be not lawfull, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> yet the fault is not ours, but theirs that impose them.</p>
            <p>Vnlawfull commands in matters of Religion especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> cannot be obeyed without sinne, <hi>Hosea</hi> 5.11. and it is a sinne to walk after them many wayes: First, against God, frō whose Authoritie so much is derogated as is ascribed to mans ordinance in those matters, 2 <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.22.23. Secondly, against our Superiours, whose con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences are offended, they being imboldened to sinne, whilest they thinke that to be lawfully imposed, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178375:14"/>is by us receaved &amp; obeyed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.12. Thirdly, against the present age &amp; posteritie, whilest by our yeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to unwarrantable impositions, the reformation is hindered. Fourthly, against our selves, by partaking in other mens sinnes, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>This rather concernes the Minister, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> whose action it is, then the people.</p>
            <p>Whatsoever worship is offered up to God by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansv v </seg>
               </label> is in their name, and so the action of the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly then present, who are to declare their assent by say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Amen,</hi> if it be lawfull, if otherwise to call upon their Minister to fulfill the Ministrie which he hath receaved of the Lord, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. and as occasion shall require to proceed further to declare their dislike in such a maner as is meet, either by absenting themselves from it, or by other wayes declaring their dislike, so as the whole Church may take notice of it.</p>
            <p>What if one read on a Booke, or talke with others, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> or doe some thing else in the bottome of the Seat, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the Liturgie is reading, is not it sufficient?</p>
            <p>Publike disorders must bee publikely witnessed against, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20. that the Church may be edefied, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> if that cannot be done, or be to no purpose, men ought to absent themselves from that act of worship wherein they cannot joyne warrantably.</p>
            <p>But I cannot joyne with the Church in some ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God without these as, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> in the reading of the Scriptures, and in the Sacraments, and if I joyne not in Liturgie, I may loose many good Sermon in Churches that are much frequented and thronged.</p>
            <p>The answer which the Ministers of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the five Articles enacted at <hi>Perth,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> whereby
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:178375:15"/>they justifie their not communicating at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble where the gesture is changed, and distributing the Elements by the Communicants is wanting, will serve for this purpose also by a parrety of Reason; they say, wee are all bound to maintaine the puretie &amp; integritie of Gods ordinances &amp; therefore cannot communicate in these cases: no man will be so carelesse of his legge or arme, as to suffer them to bee cut off, but will venture himselfe for their preservation, or the preservation of the least joynt of his fingers, howbeit they be not such noble parts of the body as the head and heart, without which the body cannot subsist, farre lesse ought we to tollerate such a horrible stumbling blocke, as, kneeling in the act of receaving the Sacramentall elements eating and drincking, whosoever countenances such Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is accessarie to that deformation and mutillation; for if none would communicate with the Ringleaders and Introducers, they woul be forced to desist, &amp; had desisted long agoe, for shame: the kneeler is the theef, the communicant is the receaver. Apply this to the joyning in the Liturgie upon the same ground. Againe, they adde, some thinke they may, if they have libertie to sit themselves, and to reach to the nearest, but they should not looke to their owne personall priviledges, but to the libertie of the whole Church and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation whereof they are members. If some Citizens would give way to the enemies, upon condition of their injoying their owne libertie, would not they be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Traitors, and betrayers of the Cittie? But you will say, Shall I separate from a Church? I answere, when a Congregation is devided, that part which doth not communicate, is a part of that Church as well as that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178375:15"/>which doth, and both make up one Congregation, or Church, howbeit they be devided in that particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as both partes of the house makes but one house, notwithstanding there be a rift in the wall, yet it is hard say you, to want the benefit and comfort of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but what comfort or benefit can you finde if you be accessarie to the introduction of such alterations,<note place="margin">The great sacriledge of the Church of Rome.</note> &amp; setting of such stumbling blockes, in the Congregation? when we cannot communicate but by committing a sinne, our forbearance is no contempt, and the Lord, who hath promised to be a little Sanctuarie to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when they were to be scattered among the heathen, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 11.16. will supply our wants.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 204.</note> Doctor <hi>Feathly</hi> saith, That neither the onely nor principall thing to be regarded in the Sacrament, is our benefit, but Gods glory, and testification of our obedience, to his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. <hi>Beza</hi> saith,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Conf. Chap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Wee cannot seeme to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, who are not permitted to partake of them as they are appointed by the Lord; farre be it from us to imagine any causes of necessitie by which wee may vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Lords ordinance. This answere may serve, if the case were so hard that they could not have the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of the right &amp; pure administration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments elsewhere. But (praysed be God) as yet they may have it not farre from the doores; these be the wordes, apply them to the case in question, and answere your selfe.</p>
            <p>The Rule is cleere, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>2</label> wee must not doe evill that good may come thereon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. for an unlawfull act wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly and willingly done, defileth a man, <hi>Marke</hi> 7.27. &amp; to them that are defiled nothing is pure, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.15. no not the very Sacrament, nor any other Ordinance of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178375:16"/>God, and God doth more strictly binde us to abstaine from what hee forbids, then to doe what is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for almost all the Commandements of the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue are negative, &amp; negative commandements binde alwayes, and to every moment of time, so doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatives, but as circumstances require, so that if the question bee, seeing I cannot doe both, which shall I choose and refuse? the answere is, Obedience is better then Sacrifice, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.32. I must rather forbeare the good how great soever, then commit the evill how little soever, therefore this order is set for our obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, first eschew evill, then doe good, <hi>Psalm.</hi> 34.14. <hi>Esay</hi> 1.16.17. Againe, not the want but the contempt of the Sacrament shall be imputed to men for sinne, for the Passeover was as necessarie to be receaved of the Iewes once a yeare, as the Lords Supper is at any time now, and yet in case of legall pollution, or being from home in a journey, they were warranted to be absent from it, <hi>Num.</hi> 10.13.</p>
            <p>Prayer &amp; Preaching, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>3</label> &amp; Prayer and Reading, &amp; Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at the Sacraments are different ordinances, though they ought to goe together in their right use, yet they may be severed &amp; therefore wee must looke that they are lawfull, and distinct one from another: the lawfull Preaching of the worde will not excuse us for joyning with unlawfull Prayers, the goodnesse of Preaching will not beare out the corruptions in Praying the good wheat will not make the Tares good, but the Tares ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will choake the wheat, so corruptions in one ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance will not better another, nor be bettered by it, but corrupt it, &amp; make it worse in time, as wee so despising of Prophecying and a slight account of the Ministers
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178375:16"/>gifts in Preaching, accompany the stinting of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters to mens formes in praying, for the imposers thereof accounts the Church sufficiently provided for with the Liturgie and the Book<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, Homelies, &amp; val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues the Ministers more for their conformitie in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then for their gifts in Preaching.</p>
            <p>Some finde by experience that they have receaved much good &amp; comfort in the Worde and Sacraments, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>6</label> even when they have joyned in that Booke prayer and stinted Service, therefore it is lawfull.</p>
            <p>I denie the Argument: For, first, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
               </label> the lawfulnesse of actions must bee proved not by events, but by Rule, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.8. Secondly, by such reasoning a man may prove all Popish vanities lawfull; as, kneeling in the act of receaving, for they have had much comfort in so receaving their Maker; so, for Organs &amp; Instruments of Musicke, to be used in singing Psalmes in the Church, because some have found their hearts much cheared &amp; lifted up to Heaven almost thereby; so, for Images to be used, for the help of mens devotion in worshipping God, because some have found their spirits much stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up by them; so, for saying over so many <hi>Pater nosters, Ave Maryes,</hi> and Prayers by number on their Beads, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause many have found much cōfort therin. Secondly, That good &amp; comfort whereof men speake, is in some a meere fancy, arising from a false peace within, caused by ignorance, or the silence of conscience; in some, a meere delusion of Sathan, whereby he holdeth super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious persons in love with their blinde devotions; in some others, a common worke of the spirit, which hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites may feel in the ordinances, without being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178375:17"/>in what they doe. Lastly, It in some a sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and saving worke of the spirit, and then it is Gods blessing upon his owne ordinance, whereunto they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their whole hearts, not upon mens owne warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able devises, wherewith they are defiled through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, God mercifully pardoning these ignorances, though hee is displeased at their inventions, <hi>Isal.</hi> 99.8. But this helpeth not them who are willingly ignorant of any duty, or slight any knowne sinne; <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.16.</p>
            <p>However, it pleaseth our mercifull God to passe by the times of our ignorance, yet now hee calls upon us to repent, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. If now wee shall shut our eyes against the light that is offered, or take liberty to sinne, because wee thinke the matter is not great, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or blessing can wee expect hereafter in any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.16.17.</p>
            <p>To conclude, If reading the Liturgie bee the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which Gods Word allowes, we are bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to apply our selves to it, as Gods ordinance, &amp; not wee onely, but also all the Churches throughout the World, If not, we are bound to witnesse against it: Consider what I say, and the LORD give you understanding in all things. What I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is the perswasion of my heart, yet I submit it to examination of the godly Learned by Scripture.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>